Hi everyone, in today's video,
we will go through our roadmap,
phase 3, prompt engineering.
In this, we will talk about the
first one, UI versus API,
calling LLMs via API.
We are going to learn about all of
these concepts.
And I just wanted to give you a
quick heads up.
We have already completed phase 2.
The whole thing has been completed
in phase 2.
And in the phase 1 also,
we completed almost every single
thing.
There are two topics.
We will learn these two topics
during the project section.
Because, if you learn individually,
you will feel very disconnected.
And I don't want you to be feeling
that way.
So the first thing what we are going
to learn is, how UI is different
from the API.
I have come to ChatGPT.
And I will give a prompt like this.
Create a mermaid flowchart of how an
agent decides which tool to call,
including the loopback when the tool
fails.
Show it as a clear top to bottom
diagram.
And let's click on enter.
We are using 5.5 model here.
And if you look at this,
the code is writing here,
ChatGPT.
And after writing the code,
it will give you the output in this
UI.
So you can see the plot or you can
see the chart directly.
Now what we are going to do is,
we will go to the notebook in Google
Colab.
And here also, I am using the same
ChatGPT model.
I will show you exactly what happens
in the later part.
And I am giving the same prompt
here.
And let's execute this.
And see what will come here.
Okay, let's wait until it gets.
See, here we have written the same
code as before.
But it is not rendering the image.
And as we see here, we can't see the
image directly.
Why?
Because when you communicate to any
of these LLM models via UI,
there are a lot of things happening
behind them.
System prompts, tools,
all of these rendering.
A lot of things that are happening
in the back end.
You cannot do it while using API.
Now let's take one more example.
What's today's date?
And what are the three biggest AI
releases this weekend?
I will put it here.
And let's see what happens in the
UI.
So today's date is 30 June 2026.
Now it is searching all of the
internet.
And based on the results in the
internet, it will give you the
answer.
Let's wait.
Okay, latest model releases.
It is thinking about what we need.
And it read all of these things.
And based on these information,
we got the answer like this.
So what did it give?
Anthropic Sonnet 5 and GPT 5.63.
Mutant Longcat 2.1.
But the same prompt, when we give to
the API via Google Colab,
do you think you will get the same
answer?
No.
Because when you are using the LLMs
via API,
you don't have access to any of the
tools.
Look, it gave the date.
Why it gave the date?
Because we are currently using 5.5
model from OpenAI.
And 5.5 has inbuilt date tool call
function.
So that is why it is giving the
date.
And if you look at the news,
I don't have the live web access in
this chart.
So I can't liably identify it.
You might have understood by now.
The GPT model you are talking in the
UI is different.
code is different.
So the same thing for Claude
Anthropic,
Gemini, Groq, any kind of models.
And one more thing,
when you are working in a company,
you cannot directly interact with
UI.
When you are building applications,
you need to interact via API.
What will you do then?
So what we will do in this video is,
we will see how you can use APIs,
how to call the APIs,
what is the code,
and how to call multiple APIs,
let's say Claude or ChatGPT or
Groq.
So let's see how to call them and
what to do.
First thing is,
in my code example,
I am showing three different models.
One is ChatGPT OpenAI models,
Anthropic Claude models,
and LLaMA models from Groq.
Now what you need to use from API
is,
you need API keys.
You can put these API keys in Google
Collab,
in the Secrets tab.
How to create API keys?
Let's say OpenAI,
OpenAI,
API key and search.
You will directly get this page,
and from here you can create your
API keys,
create secret API keys.
I have already created some API
keys,
and these keys are very important,
and you cannot share it with anyone.
So please don't share these keys
with anyone.
Similarly,
you can go with Anthropic API keys,
search,
you get this Get API key,
go here,
after going,
you will go to the console on the
top right corner,
and after entering the console,
you can create your API key via Get
API key.
If you want Groq,
you can say Groq API key,
and then go to the first link,
console.groq.com from Groq,
there is an API key on the top right
corner,
you can click on create API key,
and you will get the API key.
So those three API keys,
I have saved in Google Collab,
and named them,
Anthropic API key,
Groq API key,
and OpenAI API key.
So our first requirement is to get
the API keys,
and we got it.
Because they are ChatGPT,
Anthropic,
and paid models,
you need to have some credit card
details.
So if you look at the Anthropic,
I added $5,
and also ChatGPT,
I have added $10,
because I want to use these things.
Since Groq is free,
you don't have to add any money,
then you can directly use it for
free of cost.
Now how to communicate with these
APIs?
So to communicate like that,
we have multiple packages from
Python.
If you want to communicate with
OpenAI API,
you have a package called OpenAI,
you have to install that package.
If you want to communicate with
Anthropic Claude Models,
you have something called Anthropic.
If you want to communicate with Groq
Models,
you have Groq.
Since these are all APIs,
you can use a generic package,
which is called Requests as well.
So what are we doing here?
We are trying to install OpenAI,
Anthropic,
Groq,
and Requests.
So let's click on Execute.
Now everything is executed.
Okay, everything is executed.
Now we have the API keys in our
Google Collab.
Enable all of these to access the
notebook.
And once you enable it,
what am I doing here?
I am trying to load these API keys
in the notebook itself.
If you look at this line here,
so this says our OpenAI API key,
and then Anthropic API key,
and then Groq API key.
So using this line of code,
I am loading all of them in these
variables.
And after that,
I am importing the OpenAI package
and the Anthropic package.
And in OpenAI,
I am going to talk about the Charge
GPT 5.5 model.
That is why I am putting this
variable.
And in Anthropic,
I am going to talk about Claude
Sonnet 4.6
because it is a little bit less
costlier.
And in Groq,
I am going to use LLaMA models,
which are 70 billion parameter size.
So once you import these packages,
what do you have to do?
You need to create a client.
And using that client,
you can hit the API.
That is why I am creating the client
here,
OpenAI API client,
and Anthropic client,
and Groq to Groq client.
If you see here,
I am using a package from OpenAI for
Groq.
Why?
Because in OpenAI,
you have an option to connect via
Groq as well.
When you are doing that,
you need the URL.
So this is the URL that you need to
provide.
While connecting to the Groq
via OpenAI API.
And what is our API?
We have taken it for Groq API.
So once you load all of these
things,
you have created all of these three
clients.
And we are good to go and use the
APIs.
So let's execute this code.
So clients are ready.
GPT 5.5, Claude Sonnet 4.6,
and LLaMA models.
So see here,
I have a sample ticket.
Just wanted to give you a real time
example.
Let's say you are working in a
customer interface
per start board.
What happened here?
A customer has raised a ticket.
This is the third time I am writing.
I ordered the Aurora wireless
headphones.
What is the order number?
On June 14, for 7500 rupees.
And they arrived with a cracked left
ear cup.
I want a full refund, not a
replacement.
If I don't hear back in 48 hours,
I am doing a charge back on my card.
So here I have created a simple
ticket.
I am keeping that ticket in a
variable.
Let's execute this.
I will talk about how to use this
later on.
Let's not worry about it.
I have written it for the hook.
Now let's see how you can talk to
these APIs
via their package called requests.
What is this request package?
Because when the API communication
is happening,
from your laptop to the servers,
all of this communication happens
via HTTPS.
HTTPS communication is a single
framework by default.
So you can use the request package
and communicate via these things.
Now how to communicate using this
request package?
If you haven't watched my API
explained video,
go there and watch it.
You will get more clarity on
requests,
server, communication,
gateway,
all of these things.
So I am saying request.post.
And here I need to provide the URL.
If I want to talk to ChatGPT API,
I need to enter this URL.
And then headers.
What are headers?
If I want to hit the OpenAI,
I have the API key.
If I want to send the API key,
then only it will validate.
That's what we are doing.
By keeping the authorization as a
barrier,
you are sending your OpenAI key.
So that your message is valid
and OpenAI will give you the
response actually.
And after that,
based on what you have done,
what model are you using?
I am using OpenAI GPT 5.5 model.
And here I am providing this entire
prompt.
If you haven't looked at my prompt
engineering video,
I have explained there.
What is a role?
What is user?
What is content?
So just to summarize,
whenever you want to give a prompt
to an LLM via API,
first you need to put the role,
the user.
And what is the content the user is
asking?
Say hello in one short sentence.
I am giving this to a prompt or GPT
5.5 model.
And then you get the output in this
format.
So let's try and hit this one
and see what happens.
the output of the HTTP request is
200.
That means it's a valid API request.
And our reply is hello.
Simple.
What have we done?
We just hit the OpenAI 5.5 model via
API
and we got the reply as hello.
Very simple.
Nothing complex at all.
Now, using this request package,
since it is a bit complex to put a
URL or authorize,
they have built their own package
for charging, entropy,
etc.
So what can I do?
Here, if you remember the client
that we created at the top,
we created an OpenAI client.
And it doesn't even have a key.
By default, it will take all the
keys as well.
Now, let's use that client.
We can talk to this one.
So if you look at this one,
our OpenAI client that we created
and then we just say chart
.completions.create.
What model are we using inside this?
What is the 5.5 model?
And here is the message.
So what is the role?
What role is the system?
What is the prompt for the system?
What is the persona that you are
setting for the system?
You are a concise support agent,
max three sentences.
Now, I will give you a ticket.
I am telling you to concise that
ticket
to our RGPT 5.5 key.
And along with that,
I am providing what is the ticket
information.
What is the sample ticket?
Very simple.
So let's try to execute this
and see how it will return the
answer for us.
Look, OpenAI.
I am very sorry.
This has taken three messages.
Your order ID.
For the Aurora wireless headphones.
This is all done.
I understand.
For your chargeback concern,
we will treat this as an urgent.
So we took the ticket
and after taking the ticket,
concise the ticket and gave us the
output.
ChargePT 5.5.
Very simple.
But if I want to use the same task
with an anthropic package,
I can do
by initializing an anthropic client
and say message.create.
Here you can see
chart.completions.create
and here message.create.
Now you will have a doubt in your
brain.
What should we do if we know all
this?
That is why always documentation
is the first thing to go.
Anthropic API docs
Search and Google
documentation will come.
Click on this one and you will see
what to do.
Client.message.create.
Here we are doing the same thing.
Anthropic.message.create
Anthropic client.message.create
So you can go through these
documentation. Here we have all the
quick starts.
You can go to API reference.
You can read about all of these
things.
And then you will get to know more
details.
And here one of the important
differences is that
our system prompt
means we are giving some kind of
persona to our LLM.
In OpenAI, you have to give it like
this.
But in Anthropic,
we have to give a system variable
to that variable directly.
And then this is the message.
What is our role?
Same, let's click on this one.
So there are small changes here and
there
compared to the package of both
OpenAI and Anthropic.
And also we have the Groq.
What does Groq do?
So if you want to go understand
Groq client, what do you have to do
directly?
Groq API documentation.
Click on this one.
Groq API references.
And see how much documentation
is used to use Groq model.
You can look at this and you can
use all of these things.
Let's not go into
details for now.
And what I am doing here is Groq
client.
Since this is an OpenAI follow,
I am just following directly.
So let's click on execute.
And we got the output.
Very simple.
So what is our understanding?
Whenever you want to hit an API,
either you can hit via request
package,
or open AI package,
or Anthropic package.
So if they have their own packages,
you can use them. Otherwise,
you can directly
use request package.
But what happens when you use
request package?
You need to provide URL,
you need to provide a lot of
details.
So without giving
such details, you can use the other
packages. So you can save
this and you can screenshot this
right here
so that you can understand the
comparison between
how these different packages
differ with respect to the API
calling. And after that,
the next thing is message format.
So when I go
to ChatGPT and let's say
can you summarize
what I have
asked of you?
I gave prompt basically.
What does this do? It has access
to the history.
So let's ask first time,
let's ask Mermaid flow chart.
And second time, let's ask today's
date
and identify the top 3 papers.
So it remembers what we asked.
But when you go via
API, how does ChatGPT
work? Because every time you are
sending a request from a different
time and zone, right?
So we have something
which is called as conversation.
So what happens in this scenario
is, so let's say this is our
ChatGPT API.
For API, first time when you hit the
question, you get an answer as an
output.
That is fine. Second time when you
hit
the question, you get an answer as
an output.
But when you
want to send it third time,
can you ask a question like
can you summarize what are the
previous
things that I have asked for you?
This API does not have access to
these two, right? Then it cannot
answer.
So what you do in such a case is
when you send it third time,
you will get the question and answer
question and answer from the
previous conversations.
You will append those question
answers into this prompt in third
question and you send it via API
and you get the response back.
What are you doing here?
You are sending the conversation
that has happened before
as a system prompt
or assistant prompt and then you are
hitting the API again.
So by this, this API will know
what happened before.
It is what basically memory is.
Very simple. What should you do?
You just need to save all of the
conversations that happened before
and you send it via API.
Very simple.
So what are we doing here?
We are doing the same thing.
So what we did first is
what is the order number dimension.
So let us take this prompt
and let us execute this.
So we gave the order number
but it did not know the
order number.
So because we did not send any
conversation that happens,
what will I do?
I created a memory which is
basically a list.
Within that list,
we have the role system,
the prompt system
and the sample ticket content.
Then we have the assistant
and after that
we have the reply from the
What are the replies that we get?
So what we do next?
This is the point where we ask
our question. What order number
did I just mention?
If I give the prompt like this
or the command like this,
see, I am getting the order number
because now
OpenAI API has access to
this memory. That is
how you will maintain memory in
LLMs.
Very simple.
And the other thing is
when you look at UI,
when you type in UI,
the letters will be printed like
this.
That is what we call as streaming.
But when I hit the API here,
you will not see it as direct
printing.
You will get direct output.
It might not be intuitive,
but it is fast.
No, you have to print
one by one.
So that is where you stream in
chunks.
Hit the same API.
After hitting, you write a
for loop. In that for loop,
you are navigating through the
output
and printing one by one.
Very simple. It is what we call
as a streaming output.
I am sorry, it is printing one by
one.
Let me execute once again.
See, it is just
like a UI.
So whenever you
use UI,
when you use that UI,
all of these things are going to
happen
in the backend.
If you do not use UI,
all of these things, if you are
using via
API, you need to build it.
I hope you have learned all of these
things in this video.